# Jinson Anto Charls GAICD

0452 209 595 | <u>iinsonanto1987@gmail.com</u>

#### **Profile**

A seasoned and dedicated healthcare professional with a passion for mental health and addiction services, embodying robust leadership and team-building capabilities. Known for being approachable, inspiring staff to exceed service delivery targets, and driving improvements within the care environment. This individual brings a wealth of strategic management and community service experience, sharpening their decision-making, representation, and communication skills. With a keen interest in representing the Northern Territory at the Country Liberal Party, this person is primed to apply their substantial healthcare expertise to foster empathetic, evidence-based policy-making. Their transition to a political role is underpinned by a solid professional foundation and a profound commitment to enhancing the lives of the constituents.

# **Experience**

#### **Charles Darwin University**

• Adjunct Lecturer – July 2023 to present

#### Top End Mental Health, Alcohol and Other Drug Services, Northern Territory Health

- A/Executive Director (August 2023)
- Acting General Manager (Sep 2021, Jun 2022, Sep/Oct 2022)
- Director of Recovery and Rehabilitation Services (May 2023 Present)
- Director of Acute Services (May 2022 April 2023)
- Operations Manager (Nov 2020 Apr 2022)
- Team Manager, Mental Health Access Team (Jun 2019 Oct 2020, May June 2018)
- Team Leader/CNC, Mental Health Access Team (Dec 2017 May 2019)
- Clinical Mental Health Nurse Specialist, Mental Health Access Team (Aug Nov 2017)
- Acting Clinical Lead (leave cover 2015 2017), AOD Mandatory Assessment Unit
- Senior Assessment Clinician (Aug 2015 Aug 2017), AOD Mandatory Assessment Unit

#### Wagga Wagga Base Hospital, NSW Health

- Registered Nurse, Mental Health Unit (Feb 2013 Jan 2015)
- Registered Nurse, Emergency Department (May 2012 Jan 2013)

#### Little Flower Hospital and Research Centre

• Registered Nurse, Intensive Coronary Care Unit (May 2010 - May 2011)

#### **Education**

- Central Queensland University: MBA Leadership (Currently enrolled)
- Australian Institute of Company Directors: Company Directors Course Graduated 2022
- University of Tasmania: Graduate Certificate in Leadership (Health and Human Services) 2021
- The University of Newcastle, Australia: Master of Mental Health Nursing 2016
- The Initial Registration for Overseas Registered Nurses (IRON) program 2011
- Mahatma Gandhi University: Bachelor of Nursing and Midwifery 2010

#### **Skills & Abilities**

- Experience in strategic direction and management for MHAOD services.
- Proficient in comprehensive clinical assessments and crisis management.
- Experience in team management roles, nurturing positive psychology in the workplace.

- Comprehensive knowledge in various fields including ICCU, ED, Inpatient Acute Mental Health, Crisis Mental Health, Forensic Mental Health, Forensic Disability, and Alcohol and Other Drug Services.
- Proficient in documentation and report writing, file reviews, and evaluation.

#### Achievements

- Honorary appointment at the Charles Darwin University as Adjunct Lecturer.
- Completed Company Director's Course for governance understanding, Graduate Certificate in Leadership (Health and Human Services) for enhanced leadership skills, and a Master's degree in Mental Health Nursing for specialised knowledge in mental health and substance abuse treatment.
- Represented TEMHAODS at Royal Darwin Hospital and with other governmental and non-governmental organisations.
- Appointed as a Designated Mental Health Practitioner (DMHP) under the Northern Territory Mental Health Act and served as both a Senior Assessment Clinician and Senior Treatment Clinician under the previous Alcohol Mandatory Treatment Act.

### **Community Involvement**

- President Darwin Malayalee Association, Aug 2023 Present
- Secretary Darwin Malayalee Association, Aug 2022 July 2023
- Public Relations Officer Darwin Malayalee Association, 2021/22
- Treasurer Darwin Malayalee Association 2016/17
- Committee member/Elected Unit representative St Alphonsa Syro-Malabar Catholic Parish, Darwin 2020-2022
- College Students Union Elected Chairman, 2009/10, Little Flower College of Nursing, Angamaly, Kerala, 2008-2010

#### **Past Political Affiliations**

• Kerala Students Union, Unit President, Little Flower College of Nursing, Angamaly, Kerala, 2008-2010

# **Political Affiliations - Family**

#### **Charls Antony (Father)**

- Ex- General Secretary (2009 -2019), Kerala Cooperative Employees Front, Cooperative sector employees union with 17000 members
- Government appointed Director Cooperative Employees Welfare Board, Kerala State Government, 2011-2016
- Government appointed Director Cooperative Employees Pension Board, Kerala State Government, 2009-2011, 2016-2019

#### **Anto Antony (Father's brother)**, Member of Parliament, Pathanamthitta, India (2009 – present)

- Indian Nursing Council member from the elected representative from Parliament, 2009-2014
- Addressed the United Nations General Assembly representing India in 2014
- Member, Standing Committee on External Affairs, Government of India, 2009
- Member, Standing Committee on Energy, Government of India, 2009
- Member, Consultative Committee, Ministry of Minority Affairs, Government of India
- Member, Standing Committee on Transport, Tourism and Culture, Government of India, 2019current

• Member, Committee on Government Assurances, Government of India, 2014-2019

#### **Reference:**

https://sansad.in/ls/members/biography/4571?from=members https://www.facebook.com/AntoAntonyMP/

## **Summary of Qualifications**

**Public Healthcare Experience:** My extensive experience in the public healthcare sector has given me a deep understanding of the real-world implications of health policy decisions. This background provides me with a unique perspective on healthcare legislation and its impact on the community, and how to best serve the public interest.

**Leadership Skills:** My various leadership roles have developed my ability to direct teams, make strategic decisions, and work towards common goals. I have a demonstrated ability to inspire and motivate staff to provide exceptional service, which will translate well into leading and representing the interests of the Northern Territory in the Country Liberal Party.

**Policy Development:** I have led policy and procedure development within my healthcare roles. I have responded to ministerial queries and prepared ISR Category 1 review reports. These experiences have honed my policy-making skills, preparing me to contribute effectively in a legislative capacity.

**Community Involvement**: My active involvement in community organisations, including the Darwin Malayalee Association and the St Alphonsa Syro Malabar Parish, demonstrates my dedication to serving and improving my community. I am connected to the community's needs and concerns, which will enable me to represent them effectively in a political role.

**Communication and Representation Skills:** My experiences representing Top End Mental Health, Alcohol, and Other Drug Services at the Royal Darwin Hospital and with other governmental and non-governmental organisations have polished my communication and representation skills. I am comfortable and competent in liaising with various stakeholders, making me well-suited for a political role.

**Cultural Competency:** With over a decade in health, I deeply understand the unique needs of diverse groups. Skilled in communication, I excel at connecting with Indigenous Australians and those from Culturally and Linguistically Diverse (CALD) backgrounds, seamlessly navigating cultural nuances to foster understanding and inclusivity.

**Education:** My academic background, including Graduate Certificate in Leadership, Graduate Certificate from Australian Institute of Company Directors and a Master's degree in Mental Health Nursing, provides me with a strong understanding of both management and healthcare issues. This comprehensive knowledge base will be invaluable in a political role where varied issues need to be understood and addressed.